[Music]
welcome the busy Center lunch event and
our session about what is new related
with new denish bookkeeping act and B
Central where my colleague Alexander and
I will try to explain all those
details um I will start first with a
short introduction and continue with
what we already have inside the business
center from all those requirements as
this is something we didn't change at
all uh but after that I will continue
with new planed features as I said some
of them are already finished so my
colleague Alexander will show some of
them okay uh from 2022 when this new L
was approved we were active
investigating what to do and how to
adjust BS Center related with these
requirements even the guidelines are not
so clear in many situation we are
dedicated to certify our solution
against new Dage bookkeeping
act what is important to know Microsoft
register Beil Central Cloud version in
the first wave and solution will be
certified as a standard solution as is
this is what part Microsoft deliver
without customizations now I will go
more in details to explain the process
and what we did as well as what we are
still
doing okay first thing first as I
already mentioned Microsoft is committed
to provide full compliance to all our
customers globally so this is applicable
for Danish customers as well uh Cloud
option has an absolute Advantage as
there are not so many limitations there
because of the following uh this guiding
star we are started early with designing
and redesigning our solution what is
important here every time we saw some
required feature can be applicable for
other countries we decided to deliver
this as a global feature adding only
local Danish flavor but for all other
changes uh even they are fully local
they will be delivered as extensions
without changing W1 base for Danish
Market um in this moment we are closing
the most of requirement and some of them
are already finished but some of them
are close to be
done uh let's first see what we already
have inside the busy Central not
everything but what is required with uh
Danish bookkeeping act and what we
already have inside the bus Central
without any
customization um the standard digital
bookkeeping system must contain fields
for company to provide information on
following matters when record each
indidual transaction this is related
with transaction date amount receipt
number transaction text exchange rate
and conversion factor for or um
currencies not in a local currency not
in the Dage crown and when you look in B
Central all transaction enter in B
Central contain already transaction date
amount uh document number uh description
is a transaction text and all ENT
general ledger um transactions are start
stored in um exclusively in a local
currency and if original do uh if
original document has currency other
than Danish Crown this information
exists in subledger connected with
general ledger entry for example
customer Ledger entry vendor Ledger
entry
so um then we need to provide uh full
audit Trail for recorded transactions
what it means system assigns the
following registration date for each uh
recorded transaction conse transaction
number or ID for each recorded
transaction initial or similar to the
person who has a recorded transaction
system also save changes to recording
what does it mean uh that incorrect
entries in a system must be corrected in
the new entries and record transaction
cannot be changed backdated or deleted
and of course in a busy Central and a
trail uh record is created for every
transaction everything is in general ler
register upon posting this register they
already have created it and even
creation time together with user ID as a
person who recorded the section for each
odit Trail record register you can also
find uh you can also find the view
number column which specific System
created number of general ledger
register and of course you cannot delete
uh any entries you cannot change date
this is already inside so if you want to
make some correction you need to uh
create new entry uh as a corrected entry
stere what else uh the needs to provide
bank
reconciliation uh is the first part you
can see we need to provide minimum one
of the options and P Center provide the
solution that means this requirement of
digital standard bookkeeping system
where we need to support possibility of
reconciling the company bookkeeping with
a company bank account it supports
Advanced bank reconciliation allowing
you to import electronic bank statement
in various format including CSV what is
mandatory and automatically reconcile
them with the back transaction in the
system this is first requirement and
this is of three uh
mandatory what is else require the
additional requirement that each bank
account is linked to an account in a
chart of account through a sign a bank
account posting group this is already in
a bus Central so reconciliation exists
for payment and bank accounts and there
is already clear difference in the bank
accounts Ledger entry for uh um
reconcile and not reconcile
entries now it was shortly what we
already had and what we already have in
the system now let's make a look in new
plan features all new plan features are
part of 2023 release wave two but they
will not all of them will be available
in October they will be finishing next
minors and ready for the beginning uh
new calendar year so we will certify
everything on time and you can start
using them from the beginning of next
year what first uh mandatory digital
vouchers this is now new Global feature
we decided to create this as a global
feature in in all other countries it can
be voluntarily used but it will be
enforcing in Denmark there will be
mandatory setup for purchase and sales
documents but you can set up additional
entries as you want to use there are
different uh entry types you can choose
to set up such as sales document
purchase document different type of
journals and what it means you in in
Denmark you will be by default enforced
to attach purchase document before
posting it you cannot post document if
you don't attach uh scan or document or
PDF or some kind of purchase document uh
related with your purchase invoice or
purchase gate memo and in the sales
system will automatically create sales
documents and attach it because you
don't need to create something manually
it will be full automation syst will
create PDF from your U sales invoice or
your C whatever and automatically
attached to your transaction more about
this feature uh you can see in separate
session about uh mandatory digital
vouchers and I will encourage you to go
to watch this session it will be
important for
you now
sft sft module is created on the top of
our audit file export
app uh it contains not only sft export
but much more part of this package are
Danish public standard chart of account
and public standard V chart of account
so when you run it you will
automatically get you will automatically
get standard chart of accounts and your
obligation is only to map this uh stand
public standard chart of account with
your existing chart of account in the
system eventually uh you can choose to
set up then standard chart of account as
your main primary chart of account in
the system if you want but this is not
mandatory you can use any type chart of
account as a primary and you just need
to map it with the public standard chart
of
account then there is an sft file export
as required by the local authorities and
we use the same model for export
bookkeeping data to r c basis as a CSV
file so the same model will export both
of these sft and CSV file you can just
choose which file you want to export and
how to configure them and now my
colleague Alexander will show you how
you can use it in the
practice thank you
Alexander first of all to start using
soft expert you need to map your
existing chart of accounts to the
standard chart of accounts to do this
you open J account mapping page I
already created a new document here and
then on the left side of the table part
we see the list of existing jail
accounts and for each of them we need to
map uh them to the standard chart of
accounts this is a list that was
pre-approved
by Danish tax
authorities and after we done with
this we go to V posting setup for soft
and here we need to set the three Fields
starting date it's the date from which
the V posting setup is valid and we also
need to set these
sales uh and purchase what reporting
codes these are filled from the list of
VT reporting codes that are also
predefined uh by Danish tax authorities
and then we proceed with the
expert so we go to audit document
we create a new one the exper format is
set
automatically and we select the J
account mapping that we created
before if necessary we can adjust
starting and end date the of the period
in which the data will be
collected and then if you want to
collect to our data in the background we
can turnone the a parallel processing
option but in our case we don't need
them so we start
expert and after it's done download a
zip archive with
the XML files inside and these
files
contain our data in the sft
format thank you Sasha
uh now I want to show more requirements
uh now little bit more about name handle
notification and
registration uh if the company is not
registered with name hand registered a
notification about that will appear on
top screen together with instruction how
to register there this is mandatory
requirement uh with this new bookkeeping
act and now if the company is registered
already in M handle busy Center we check
if c number in the company information
page exist as registered in an M handle
and if it exists the message will not
appear actually it just disappear if
previously existed and this company will
be marked as a register in M handle uh
how does it work business Central is
using the API call to verify in the
provided CVR number CV number is
actually in register number in company
information and if this number um page
exist in the Leger entity in registering
M handle uh now we will show this again
as a Dem so Alexander will show how it
look like in a practice Sasha can you
continue thank you Alexander when we
loging into our business Central tenant
we see a notification that the company
is not registered in the enm handle
service to register our company we open
the link in the notification we cck on
it the accept customer consent and the
website for name handle service is
opened and here we register our company
with its CV number and after we done
with the
registration we return to the business
Central we open company information page
and we set the company's CV number into
the registration no
field and after the field is set the
notification
disappears thank you Sasha as you can
see this is not so complic ated part but
this is mandatory this is required and
one more thing if you do not register
your company in M handle you will not
use uh you will not be uh situation to
use invoicing because this is mandatory
so you must first register you must have
all this information there so you can
continue with um uh invoicing and when
we are with be voicing more feature uh
This Time Again n handle and invoicing
uh just natural
continuation uh what about that uh
invoicing in Denmark will be based on
eents core module for our Global Market
this is what we are deliver for all
countries and on the top of this module
user can choose local format obl and P
B3 and this additional app would also
have connectors to the third party
access points for documents and message
exchange with an M
handle that means it will be
localization on top of our e document
core and I suggest to look in
independent session how invoicing works
so you can get a clue about completely
process as it will be very similar there
would not be such a big difference in
Denmark then it is also requirement that
new register standard bookkeeping
software must support the reporting of V
via Danish tax agency V
API uh that means busy Central will
support V submission in Denmark through
Define
apis this is uh this app is still work
in progress and it will be finished soon
so it will be ready for the beginning of
usage of new BKP G and certification
process um and now about storage of
transaction in digital vouchers for five
years this is probably one of the most
controversial requirements but this is
one of definitely must to deliver this
is definitely obligation we must deliver
it that means our system our standard
bookkeeping system as a busy Central
must support the storage of recorded
bookkeeping transactions in digital
vouchers for five years and this data
must be not changed PD or deleted by
user or
administrator uh this also means
customer cannot delete production
company once it is
registered and even if customer delete
whole environment Microsoft must still
keep all those data and provide them to
authorities if required this is the
law uh if customer is active on our
subscription all those data exist in a
database and customer can provide them
to the authorities without any problem
but we as a software providers have an
obligation to keep these data for five
years even if customer go to bankruptcy
or stop paying subscription or and
change the AP software or try to delete
and hide the data
on the other side based on gdpr
requirements we cannot keep more than
required so all data kept by Microsoft
after five years will be deleted it is
important to explain we will not delete
your data in your database this is not
something Microsoft will do it and uh
only what we are talking we will delete
uh all data related foret transaction
and vouchers backups that means
something what Microsoft must keep for
author ities we will keep only for five
years after your last fiscal year and
every time and this is older five years
we will remove this data keeping uh um
jdpr
standards uh this solution will be
automatically set up and this is still
work in progress uh we are we are
finishing the these procedures but it
will be on a time as I said for
certification uh of
product um yeah uh before close this
session uh I would like to invite you to
actually to watch all session because if
I'm not wrong 35 sessions are the really
great new functionalities but minimum
what is really connected with Danish uh
bookkeeping act this is uh session about
using of enforced digital vouchers then
introduction to invoicing and what is
new legislation localization definitely
um I would recommend to watch this
session it will be important for all
denish companies for other companies as
well as but especially for Danish
companies uh yes uh you have few links
very important for bus Central if you
cannot remember all of them try not to
forget uh AKA Ms bco all because you can
find all important links there so
definitely try to not to forget this
link and yes uh I would like to say
thank you I hope we demystify all
details related with new Dage
bookkeeping act and clarify some
details um yeah I hope but definitely
probably some uh new questions will
appear and I'm inviting you
to uh log in for our Q&A session where
Sasha and I uh will try to explain all
details about maybe some missing topics
so uh it will be yes October 11th so
please uh join the q& session and we
will try to uh clarify and explain all
these
details one more time thank you and my
in
name